<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation, anent persons travelling to or from this kingdom.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1643</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52528937</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52528937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178992)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2775:63)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation, anent persons travelling to or from this kingdom.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, Printer to their most excellent Majesties,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Royal arms at head of text; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Da. Moncreif, Cls. Secreti Concilis.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Given under Our Signet at Edinburgh, the fourth day of May, and of our reign the third year, 1691.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>International travel regulations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>National security --  Law and legislation --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:178992:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>monogram of 'W' (William) superimposed on 'M' (Mary)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION,<lb/> 
               <hi>Anent Perſons Travelling to or from this Kingdom.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King and Queen of <hi>Great-Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defenders of the Faith,</signed>
               <salute>To Our Lyon King at Arms, and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren Heraulds, Macers of Our Privy Council, Purſevants, Meſſengers at Arms, Our Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially conſtitute, Greeting:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Foraſmuch, as ſeveral Perſons of late have gone from this Our Antient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>France,</hi> and others have come from <hi>France</hi> into this Kingdom, upon evil Deſigns againſt the Government; Therefore We with Advice of the Lords of Our Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Do hereby Inhibite and Diſcharge all Perſons whatſoever, who intend to go out of this Our Antient Kingdom (during this time of War,) to depart furth of the ſame, until firſt they apply themſelves to, and receive a Paſs from any one of the ſaids Lords of Our Privy Council for the time being, within Twenty Miles of the ſaids Perſons their reſidence, and in caſe there be not a Privy Counſellor within that ſpace, then any two of the Commiſſioners of Supply within the Shire, where the Perſon or Perſons crave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaids Paſſes Dwell and Reſide, who have Accepted and Qualified themſelves by Law to Act as Commiſſioners. And further, We with Advice foreſaid, Do hereby Require and Command all Perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, who ſhall come into this Kingdom, at their Entry into the ſame, to preſent their Perſons, and ſhew their Paſſes, or give a rational account of themſelves, and their buſineſs, and from whence they came, upon Oath in caſe of Suſpition, to the next Counſellor, Juſtice of Peace, Magiſtrat, or Officer of Our Army; with Certification to ſuch Perſons as ſhall preſume to go furth of this Kingdom without Paſſes, or to come into the ſame, without preſenting their Perſons and Paſſes, or giving account of themſelves as ſaid is, their Perſons ſhall be ſought for, and if apprehended, ſhall be committed Priſoners, as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons juſtly ſuſpect to be coming or going upon evil Deſigns againſt the Government. And ſicklike, We with Advice fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, Do hereby Prohibite and Diſcharge all Skippers, and Maſters of Ships or Veſſels, that they receive no Paſſengers (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their Crue, for whom they muſt be Anſwerable) aboard their Ships, or Tranſport them either abroad out of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or from abroad into this Kingdom, except ſuch as ſhall be provided with Paſſes in manner foreſaid. And We with Advice foreſaid, Do hereby Require and Command the Skippers or Maſters of any Ships, who are to go furth of this Kingdom, before they ſet Sail, to give in a Lift upon Oath, of all the Perſons aboard of their Ships, or who are to go abroad with them containing their true names and Deſignations, to the next Magiſtrat, or Juſtice of Peace, in the place from whence they are to Sail: And Requires and Commands the Skippers, or Maſters of any Ships who ſhall come into this Kingdom, before they ſuffer any of their Paſſengers to Land, or go out of their Ships, to give in Liſts in manner and to the Perſons above appointed: With Certification to the ſaids Maſters or Skippers, if they failȝie to give in the foreſaid Liſts, their Ships and Veſſels ſhall be Arreſted, and their Perſons ſecured, until they be proceeded againſt as Diſobeyers of Our Authority and the Law, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors of Rebels and Suſpected Perſons: And We hereby Require and Appoint the Perſons foreſaids, to whom Paſſes are Appointed to be preſented by Paſſengers who ſhall come into this Kingdom, with all convenient Diligence, to Tranſmit to the Clerks of Our Privy Council a particular Accompt of ſuch Paſſengers with their Paſſes, as ſhall be preſented to them from time to time, with the foreſaids Liſts to be given in by the Skippers or Maſters of Ships, as ſaid is, as they will be Anſwerable. And to the effect Our Pleaſure in the Premiſſes may be known, Our Will is herefore, and We Charge you ſtraitly and Command, that incontinent theſe our Letters ſeen, ye paſs to the Mercat-Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and to the Mercat-Croſſes of the whole remanent Head-Burghs of the ſeveral Shires and Stewartries within this Kingdom, and there, in ou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Name and Authority, by open Procla-mation, make Intimation and Publication of the Premiſſes, that none may pretend ignorance, as ye will anſwer to Us thereupon. The which to do We commit to you, conjunctly and ſeverally Our full Power, by theſe Preſents, delivering them by you, duly execute and indorſed again to the bearer.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under Our Signet at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>the Fourth day of <hi>May,</hi> And of Our Reign the third Year, 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per Actum Dominorum Sti. Concilij.
<hi>DA. MONCREIF,</hi> Cls. Secreti Concilij.</signed>
               <lb/>
GOD ſave King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to Their moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſties, Anno Dom.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
